Guide to the Wilmarth Sheldon Lewis Papers
The Lewis Walpole Library
- Subject Files, 1903–1979; Series V; 2.1; 5 boxes
  - Old age, 1953–1972 (Box 286, Folder 1)
  - Oppenheimer, Robert, 1954–1955 (Box 286, Folder 2-3)
  - Painting, 1960–1971 (Box 286, Folder 4)
  - Poetry, 1940–1964 (Box 286, Folder 5)
  - Prose, 1954–1974 (Box 286, Folder 6)
  - Quotations, undated (Box 286, Folder 7)
    A card file with a first card stating in an unidentified hand: "Poets & Authors Quoted by WSL" and "This file contains quotes from WSL's favorite poets & authors."
  - Religion, 1947–1970 (Box 286, Folder 8)
  - Sexual revolution, 1966–1975 (Box 287, Folder 1)
  - Shakespeare, 1949–1979 (Box 287, Folder 2)
  - Sixteen-to-One Mine, 1965–1966 (Box 287, Folder 3)
  - Social revolution, 1965–1968 (Box 287, Folder 4)
  - Sports, 1950–1952 (Box 287, Folder 5)
  - Trustees, 1948–1978 (Box 287, Folder 6-7)
  - Watergate, 1972-1974 (Box 287, Folder 8)
  - Word usage, 1974–1977 (Box 287, Folder 9)
  - Yale May Day, 1970 (Box 287, Folder 10)
  - Youth, 1966 (Box 287, Folder 11)
- Real Estate Records, 1926–1980; Series VI; 6.05; 9 boxes + 4 broadsides
  Series VI is organized into four subseries: California, Connecticut, District of Columbia, and Rhode Island.
  The series holds the extant records for real estate owned by the Lewises. The papers range from legal documents such as deeds and rental agreements, to architectural and garden plans, and correspondence with architects and contractors. Also here are items that cover the social aspects of their homes including guest books, breakfast request cards, and letter paper.
  - California
    Wilmarth Lewis co-owned the Colusa Ranch, consisting of 1217 acres of land on the East River five miles north of Colusa, California. He was a one-quarter owner with his brother Azro, and after Azro's death with his daughter Joan Lewis Danforth. The partners had both oil and gas leases on the property, as well as leases for cattle grazing. Other income sources were farm crops including safflower, rice, prunes, and a variety of beans.
    The records here are primarily financial and legal.
    - Humble Oil Company, 1952–1956 (Box 288, Folder 1)
    - General correspondence, 1957–1969 (Box 288, Folder 2-7)
    - General correspondence, 1970–1978 (Box 289, Folder 1-3)
  - Connecticut, Farmington
    The Lewises owned five houses in Farmington over the years, but lived in only one: the General Solomon Cowles house at 154 Main Street. Four of the five properties are neighboring homes along Main Street, and were either rented out or resold to new owners. Records for those properties appear in this series.
    Records for the fifth property, the Hart-Deming house at 80 Main Street, which Annie Lewis deeded to Miss Porter's School, are filed in the Annie Burr Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 21), Series II, Personal Papers (Boxes 23, 53, and 54).
    The properties were thoroughly researched by Mabel Hurlburt for her census of Farmington homes in a project underwritten by Annie Burr Lewis in the early 1950s. The resulting card file, with additional worksheets and photoographs, are held by the Farmington Public Library, and are accessible through the library's website (http://farmingtonlibraries.org/farmington-homes/).
    - General Solomon Cowles house, 154 Main Street
      Wilmarth Lewis purchased the Cowles House in 1924, and following his 1928 marriage to Annie Burr Auchincloss, made several additions to the house to accommodate his growing collections.
      The Cowles House is known for its fine carved woodwork and paneling in several rooms. The house was described in two articles by John Cornforth, "The Cowles-Lewis House, Farmington: the Home of Mr. Wilmarth S. Lewis," in Country Life, 163, no. 4216 (April 27, 1978): 1150-53, and 163, no. 4217 (May 4, 1978): 1230-33. The interior woodwork was covered in The White Pine Series of Architectural Monographs. A measured drawing of the fireplace wall in the Morning Room, by Yale University student Richard A. Kimball, is in the library's collection and can be located by searching in the online catalog.
      - Delano and Aldrich alterations
        - Articles of Agreement for alterations and additions, 1928 (Box 290, Folder 1)
        - Drawings, 1928 (Box 339 (Broadside))
          Four drawings: 101, Foundation and Cellar Plan; 102, ground floor plan with four elevations; 201 and 203, 1/2 and 3/4-inch scale details millwork in New Library.
        - Drawings, 1928–1929 (Box 340 (Broadside))
          Thirteen drawings: 203, 205-208, 210, 212-215, 216, 219 showing details of millwork for doors, windows, cupboards, stairs, library mantel, bookcases in living room, and layout of pantry. Also present: undated drawing of "new bath rm at 2nd fl."
        - Drawings, 1928–1929 (Box 341 (Broadside))
          Fourteen drawings: 301-302, 305-307, 310-311, 315, 319, 324-326, and two unnumbered drawings showing details for millwork for doors, windows, kitchen cupboards, and the fireplace mantel in the library.
        - Drawings, 1928–1929 (Box 342 (Broadside))
          Thirteen drawings: 303-304, 308, 312-314, 317-318, 322-323, 327-328, and one unnumbered drawing (with blueprint copy) showing details of millwork for doors, windows, library bookcases, louvers, closets, mantel, and terrace garden.
      - Kimball & Husted alterations
        Architect Richard A. Kimball (1900-1997) was a friend of the Lewises, and invoved in serveral projects at the houses owned by the couple.
        Addition of master bedroom and second floor hallway.
        - "Proposed Alterations to House of W. S. Lewis, Esq.", 1936 May 22 (Box 290, Folder 2)
          Elevation showing master bedroom addition; graphite on tracing paper.
        - Correspondence, 1936–1940 (Box 290, Folder 3)
      - Gugler, Kimball & Husted alterations
        - Specifications for addition to library, undated (Box 290, Folder 4)
          For North Library and Office addition.
        - Correspondence, 1946–1959 (Box 290, Folder 5-6)
      - Tennis court, 1939–1949 (Box 290, Folder 7)
      - Garden designs
        - "Colonial Garden" and "Court Garden," by Harold Steck, 1929 (Box 337 (Oversize), Folder 4)
          Two drawings, graphite and colored pencil on paper, for a gardens in the courtyard between the New Library and squash court; designed for Annie Burr Lewis.
        - "A Plan" and "Shady Border," by Amy L. Cogswell, 1929, 1940 (Box 337 (Oversize), Folder 5)
          Two plans in blueprint.
        - "Rose Garden for Mrs. Wilmarth Lewis", 1939 (Box 337 (Oversize), Folder 6)
          Two plans, not signed, graphite and ink on paper mounted on pulpboard, with names of specific roses and their location.
        - "Preliminary Plan for the garden of Mrs. Wilmarth S. Lewis," by Umberto Innocenti-Richard K. Webel, 1945 October (Box 337 (Oversize), Folder 7)
        - Sketch of trees and Japanese yew hedge to be added to garden, undated (Box 337 (Oversize), Folder 8)
          Graphite on tracing paper, with annotations on verso by Annie Lewis.
        - On Dawn Redwood, by Willard Hartman, 1963 May (Box 290, Folder 8)
        - Planting book, 1968 (Box 290, Folder 9)
          A 1940 day book with minimal notes from 1968 on planting times for the garden.
      - Social records
        The Lewises kept guest books at their homes, into which their visitors signed their names and occasionally wrote comments.
        - Guest register, 1926 March–1979 September (Box 291)
          Arthur Guiterman's A Book of Hospitalities and a Record of Guests (New York: Barse and Hopkins, 1910), OCLC 84668547 which was a gift to Wilmarth Lewis from Kate and Brewster Jennings, was used as the Cowles House guest register. In addition to their guests' signatures, the Lewises would later add to the pages photographs taken while the guests were in residence.
        - Index to visitors, undated (Box 292)
          Wilmarth Lewis began an alphabetical card index of visitors signed into the Book of Hospitalities (Box 291), to record the pages on which each guest's signature appeared. A gold-tooled leather-covered box, stamped with the Lewises's initials, was made by Sangorski and Sutcliffe to hold the cards. On January 10, 1980, Lewis's secretary Ruth Day filed a card at the front of the box stating "There have been 822 overnight guests from 1926-1979."
        - Tally of overnight guests, circa 1980 (Box 290, Folder 10)
          Likely typed by Ruth Day, the list accounts for the 822 guests at the Cowles House; in aggregate, she notes, overnight guests were accomodated for a total of 8 years, 3 months, and 5 days between 1926 and 1979.
        - Library and print room, 1929–1980 (Box 290, Folder 11)
        - Games Record Book, 1932–1936 (Box 293, Folder 1)
          Recording scores tallied for games of squash, backgammon, duck pin bowling, and tennis.
      - "Household Inventory", undated (Box 293, Folder 2)
        A small three-ring binder with alphabetical tabs in which was kept records of chimney and window cleaning, staff addresses, and other notes about house maintenance. Under the tab "S" is an itemized list of silver objects owned by the Lewises, with some provenance notes.
      - Stationery items
        - Breakfast order forms, undated (Box 293, Folder 3)
        - Breakfast orders fulfilled, 1966–1979 (Box 293, Folder 4-6)
        - Bridge score pads, undated (Box 293, Folder 7)
        - Engraved invitations, undated (Box 293, Folder 8)
          Engraved invitations with blanks to fill in for specific days and times
        - Letter paper, undated (Box 293, Folder 9)
        - Placecards from dinners held, undated (Box 294, Folder 1)
      - Notes to staff, 1971, undated (Box 294, Folder 2)
        Notes left by Wilmarth Lewis.
      - Leases to State Board of Fisheries and Game, 1948-1974 (Box 294, Folder 3)
      - Water rights agreement, 1945 (Box 294, Folder 4)
    - Cowles/Sage house, 130 Main Street
      - Correspondence and documents, 1961–1963 (Box 294, Folder 5)
    - Root house, 158 Main Street
      - Correspondence and documents, 1941–1942 (Box 294, Folder 6)
      - Works Progress Administration photographs, 1938 (Box 294, Folder 7)
        Photographs of decorated walls in a second-floor bedroom.
      - Repairs, 1944–1955 (Box 294, Folder 8)
    - Wadsworth/Chase/Hoppin house, 164 Main Street
      - Correspondence and documents, 1933–1950 (Box 294, Folder 9)
    - Tunxis Street tract, 1933–1950 (Box 294, Folder 10)
  - District of Columbia
    The Lewises had two homes in the Georgetown section of the city during the years Wilmarth Lewis worked at the Office of Strategic Services. The first was a house they rented at 3201 P Street, NW, before purchasing 2722-2726 N Street, NW. Photographs of the exteriors of the houses can be found in the Lewises' photograph collection (LWL MSS 22).
    - 3201 P Street, NW, 1941–1942 (Box 294, Folder 11)
    - 2722-2726 N Street, NW
      - Correspondence and documents, 1942–1946 (Box 294, Folder 12)
      - Guest book, 1942–1944 (Box 294, Folder 13)
  - Rhode Island, Newport
    John Auchincloss (1810-1876) and Elizabeth Buck Auchincloss (1816-1902), the grandparents of Annie Lewis, purchased seaside property in Newport in 1852, and built a home there in 1857. When Hugh D. Auchincloss (1858-1913) and his wife Emma Jennings Auchincloss (1861-1942) inherited Hammersmith Farm, the house had been replaced by a large shingle-style home (built 1887-1888). Upon Emma's death, their children divided the property. Hugh Jr. (1897-1976) acquired the main house and Annie Lewis took a smaller gambrel-roof eighteenth-century house (the Jahleel Brenton farmhouse, 1720). Known as "The Castle," it was renovated by the Lewises and they spent their summers there.
    - Correspondence, 1943–1970 (Box 295, Folder 1-2)
      Filed here is correspondence with Auchincloss family members, architects Gugler, Kimball and Husted, decorator Elisabeth Draper, and various contractors; a building permit was issued in February 1946 for renovations of the house. Also present is a letter from Providence architect John Hutchins Cady regarding the age of the Brenton house.
    - Specifications for Alterations, undated (Box 295, Folder 3)
      Prepared by architects Eric Gugler and Richard A. Kimball.
    - Letter paper, 1952 (Box 295, Folder 4)
    - Map to "The Castle," by John Howard Benson, 1952 (Box 335 (Oversize), Folder 9)
      Ink on paper two-section map, to guide visitors to "The Castle." It was printed on the verso of the Lewises's Newport stationery featuring calligraphy by Benson.
    - Guest book, 1946–1970 (Box 295, Folder 5)
      Includes two poems by Annie Lewis's nephew Edmund ("Ted") Nash.
    - Daily News calendar with image of "The Castle," by John Howard Benson, 1950–1951 (Box 335 (Oversize), Folder 10)
      Calendar, newspaper clipping, and printed proof of Benson's drawing of "The Castle."
    - Maintenance invoices, 1963–1970 (Box 295, Folder 6)
- Financial Records, 1926–1980; Series VII; 14.39; 37 boxes
  Series VII is organized into six subseries: Bank Accounts, Investment Accounts, Yale University Accounts, Income Tax Records, Insurance Records, and Household Records.
  The series holds financial records that document the retail and investment banking pursued by Wilmarth Lewis and, to an extent, by Annie Lewis, though the couple maintained separate checking and investment accounts throughout their thirty-year marriage. The check registers here cover accounts kept over a fifty-year period by Wilmarth Lewis at commercial banks in San Francisco, Hartford, Washington, as well as with Brown, Shipley & Co. in London. His Investment Accounts were overseen by banks in New York and Hartford, and by Auchincloss, Parker & Redpath, the New York firm of Lewis's brother-in-law Hugh D. Auchincloss. The Yale University Accounts subseries holds records for the funds set up by Annie Burr Lewis; because they were largely overseen (and expenditures were authorized) by Wilmarth Lewis for twenty years after her death, all extant records were filed in his papers. The final three subseries, Income Tax Records, Insurance Records, and Household Records, pertain to both Wilmarth and Annie Lewis; there is no similar material in her papers.
  As the Lewises shared many of the expenses for keeping their homes in Farmington, Newport, and Washington, readers wishing a more complete financial picture of their lives should also consult the banking records in the Annie Burr Lewis Papers (LWL MSS 21), Boxes 29 through 46.
  - Bank Accounts
    Lewis kept checking accounts at several banks over his lifetime, and at some he maintained concurrently two types of checkbooks. Filed here are registers for both the office/desk format checks, which were often made out--generally typed--by a staff member, and second checkbook drawing from the same account in a smaller format to carry in a coat pocket or briefcase.
    - American Trust Company (San Francisco, Cal.)
      - Check registers, 1927 March–1945 March (Box 296, Folder 1-2)
    - Hartford-Connecticut Trust Company
      The Hartford-Connecticut Trust Company was created in 1919 as a merger of the Connecticut Trust and Safe Deposit Company and the Hartford Trust Company. In 1954, it merged with Phoenix Bank to become Connecticut Bank and Trust Company.
      - Check registers, 1926 August–1936 April (Box 297, Folder 1-4)
      - Check registers, 1936 April–1945 February (Box 298, Folder 1-4)
      - Check registers, 1945 February–1952 February (Box 299, Folder 1-4)
      - Check registers, 1952 February–1955 April (Box 300, Folder 1-2)
      - Pocket check registers, 1946–1953 (Box 300, Folder 3-4)
    - Connecticut Bank and Trust Company
      - Check registers, 1955 April–1960 September (Box 301, Folder 1-4)
      - Check registers, 1960 September–1965 November (Box 302, Folder 1-4)
      - Check registers, 1965 November–1972 October (Box 303, Folder 1-4)
      - Check registers, 1972 November–1973 November (Box 304, Folder 1)
      - Pocket check registers, 1960–1966 (Box 304, Folder 2)
    - Hartford National Bank and Trust Company
      - Check registers, 1962 November–1968 June (Box 305, Folder 1-7)
      - Check registers, 1968 June–1971 October (Box 306, Folder 1-6)
      - Check registers, 1971 October–1974 June (Box 307, Folder 1-6)
      - Check registers, 1974 June–1975 December (Box 308, Folder 1-4)
      - Check registers, 1976 November–1977 August (Box 308, Folder 5-6)
      - Check registers, 1977 August–1979 October (Box 309, Folder 1-7)
    - National Savings and Trust Company (Washington, D.C.)
      - Check register, 1942–1946 (Box 310, Folder 1)
    - Brown, Shipley & Co., London
      Lewis's London account was largely used for purchases made in England for his collection, and for other expenses incurred during his regular trips to the United Kingdom.
      - Check registers, statements, and cancelled checks, 1934–1945 (Box 311, Folder 1-7)
      - Check registers, statements, and cancelled checks, 1946–1953 (Box 312, Folder 1-6)
      - Check registers, statements, and cancelled checks, 1953–1958 (Box 313, Folder 1-6)
      - Check registers, statements, and cancelled checks, 1959–1964 (Box 314, Folder 1-6)
      - Check registers, statements, and cancelled checks, 1965–1973 (Box 315, Folder 1-6)
      - Check registers, statements, and cancelled checks, 1974–1978 (Box 316, Folder 1-2)
  - Investment Accounts
    - Auchincloss, Parker & Redpath, 1938–1961 (Box 317, Folder 1-18)
    - Auchincloss, Parker & Redpath, 1962–1970 (Box 318, Folder 1-8)
    - Hartford National Bank and Trust Company, 1957–1969 (Box 319, Folder 1-13)
    - Hartford National Bank and Trust Company, 1970–1976 (Box 320, Folder 1-7)
    - Hartford National Bank and Trust Company, 1977–1979 (Box 321, Folder 1-3)
    - First National City Bank, 1960–1976 (Box 321, Folder 4-5)
      The First National City Bank and Citibank accounts contained Lewis's inheritance from the Emma Brewster Auchincloss estate.
    - Citibank, 1976–1979 (Box 321, Folder 6)
    - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company of New York, 1966–1971 (Box 322, Folder 1-6)
    - Morgan Guaranty Trust Company of New York, 1972–1979 (Box 323, Folder 1-8)
  - Yale University Accounts
    - Special Fund L, 1934–1979 (Box 324, Folder 1-4)
    - Annie Burr Lewis Fund, 1949–1961 (Box 324, Folder 5-6)
      The fund was established in 1949 by Annie Lewis to underwrite the "editing, compiling, printing, and publishing a work known as 'The Yale Edition of Horace Walpole's Correspondence.'"
    - Annie Burr Lewis Fund, 1961–1980 (Box 325, Folder 1-3)
    - Lewis-Farmington Trust, 1955–1958 (Box 325, Folder 4)
  - Income Tax Records
    - Charitable donations, 1962-1979 (Box 326, Folder 1)
    - Club fees and membership dues, 1947-1979 (Box 326, Folder 2)
    - Tax forms and correspondence, 1936–1960 (Box 326, Folder 3-7)
    - Tax forms and correspondence, 1961–1968 (Box 327, Folder 1-7)
    - Tax forms and correspondence, 1969–1973 (Box 328, Folder 1-5)
    - Tax forms and correspondence, 1974–1978 (Box 329, Folder 1-5)
  - Insurance Records
    The Lewises maintained homeowners policies on their dwellings and automobiles in Connecticut and Rhode Island, as well as riders for their collections of library materials, fine art, and jewelry. In addition, as employers, they carried policies to cover workmen's compensation claims. There are no health insurance records present here.
    - Automobile, 1961–1979 (Box 330, Folder 1-2)
    - Homeowners, Connecticut, 1939–1979 (Box 330, Folder 3-7)
    - Homeowners, Connecticut, 1962–1975 (Box 330, Folder 8)
      Records of coverage arranged for collections material taken offsite.
    - Homeowners, Rhode Island, 1960–1971 (Box 330, Folder 9)
    - Workmen's Compensation, 1961–1979 (Box 331, Folder 1-2)
  - Household Records
    The subseries holds a group of miscellaneous records, including receipts and invoices, that document some of the vendors employed for the maintenance of the Lewises' property in Farmington. The invoices and receipts were sampled in 2018 from several feet of financial records in the Muniment Room.
    - Household expenses, 1958–1960 (Box 331, Folder 3)
    - Expense record book, 1964–1965 (Box 331, Folder 4)
      Notebook pages with financial entries classified under five categories: Household; Newport; WSL; Clubs; Books.
    - Expense record book, 1965-1971 (Box 331, Folder 5)
    - Expense record book, 1972–1979 (Box 331, Folder 6)
      Bound volume of entries by vendor; with alphabetical index.
    - Invoices and receipts
      - Electrical work and appliances, 1954–1979 (Box 332, Folder 1)
      - Fire suppression, 1952–1977 (Box 332, Folder 2)
      - Heating, plumbing, air conditioning, 1957–1977 (Box 332, Folder 3)
      - Interior decoration, 1952–1971 (Box 332, Folder 4)
      - Landscaping, 1956–1979 (Box 332, Folder 5-6)
        Includes invoices for annual plantings in the flower gardens and borders.
      - Office equipment and supplies, 1948–1975 (Box 332, Folder 7)
        Includes furnishings and equipment for collections storage areas as well as special supplies.
      - Painting, 1937–1960 (Box 332, Folder 8)
      - Photography and collection maintenance, 1964–1976 (Box 332, Folder 9)
      - R. F. Jones Co., 1946–1958 (Box 332, Folder 10)
        Alteration and maintenance projects completed by a Hartford firm.
      - Other expenses, 1934–1978 (Box 332, Folder 11)
- Restricted Fragile Paper, 13.0; 13 boxes
  Boxes 343-355: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the director.
  - From Series I. Correspondence
    - A - Bre (Box 343)
    - Bri - Co (Box 344)
    - Co - Fi (Box 345)
    - Fl - Har (Box 346)
    - Has - Ju (Box 347)
    - Ka - Lot (Box 348)
    - Low - Moe (Box 349)
    - Mof - Par (Box 350)
    - Pat - R (Box 351)
    - Sa - So (Box 352)
    - Sp - Wi (Box 353)
    - Wo - Z (Box 354)
    - Chapman, R. W. (Box 355)
    - Lewis Family Correspondence (Box 355)
    - Condolences upon death of Annie Burr Lewis (Box 355)
  - From Series II. Service and Affiliations (Box 355)
  - From Series III. Writings (Box 355)
  - From Series IV. Personal Papers (Box 355)
  - From Series VI, Real Estate Records (Box 355)
  - From Series VII. Financial Records (Box 355)